<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>> RogueAI</title><link>https://rogueai.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on > RogueAI</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Rogue|AI</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rogueai.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>`DRAFT` Videotel SIP TTM90</title><link>https://rogueai.github.io/posts/videotel/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rogueai.github.io/posts/videotel/</guid><description>Background In the late 80s through early 90s, Videotel was the Italian equivalent of the French Minitel: a terminal that was able to access Teletext services, provided under a subscription fee.
While in France the Minitel got quite popular, with services still active in the early 2000s, in Italy it never got to the same level of adoption, both for the subscription being quite expensive and a number of legal issues that arose among the companies involved.</description><content>&lt;h1 id="background">Background&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>In the late 80s through early 90s, Videotel was the Italian equivalent of the French Minitel: a terminal that was able
to access Teletext services, provided under a subscription fee.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While in France the Minitel got quite popular, with services still active in the early 2000s, in Italy it never got to
the same level of adoption, both for the subscription being quite expensive and a number of legal issues that arose
among the companies involved.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Although the original teletext services have long died, a Videotel can still be used as a dumb terminal when connected
to a Linux box.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="concept">Concept&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The gist of this little project is to connect the Videotel to a linux box via serial port.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Note: I&amp;rsquo;ll be using the Videotel model &lt;code>SIP TTM90/TM&lt;/code>. There are two versions of this model: the &lt;code>/TM&lt;/code> version has a
serial port on the back, while the non-&lt;code>/TM&lt;/code> version does not.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Apart from the obvious missing port, the two models also have a cosmetic difference: the front button being grey on the
model with a serial port, and red on the other one.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></content></item><item><title>Docker Compose on Synology NAS</title><link>https://rogueai.github.io/posts/synology-docker-compose/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rogueai.github.io/posts/synology-docker-compose/</guid><description>A quick howto with the steps required to setup docker and docker-compose on Synology NAS:
Install Docker package Make sure the docker network is allowed through the firewall: Navigate to: Control Panel -&amp;gt; Connectivity -&amp;gt; Security -&amp;gt; Firewall Add a custom rule Ports: Add all your exposed container ports Protocol: TCP Source IP: Specific IP -&amp;gt; Specify your docker network&amp;rsquo;s IP and subnet mask Create a scheduled task Navigate to: System -&amp;gt; Task Scheduler Create a new task for user root In Task Settings, set a User-defined script docker-compose -f /volume1/docker/docker-compose.</description><content>&lt;p>A quick howto with the steps required to setup &lt;code>docker&lt;/code> and &lt;code>docker-compose&lt;/code> on Synology NAS:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Install Docker package&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Make sure the docker network is allowed through the firewall:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Navigate to: Control Panel -&amp;gt; Connectivity -&amp;gt; Security -&amp;gt; Firewall&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add a custom rule
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ports: Add all your exposed container ports&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Protocol: TCP&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Source IP: Specific IP -&amp;gt; Specify your docker network&amp;rsquo;s IP and subnet mask&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Create a scheduled task
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Navigate to: System -&amp;gt; Task Scheduler&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Create a new task for user &lt;code>root&lt;/code>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In Task Settings, set a User-defined script
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">docker-compose -f /volume1/docker/docker-compose.yml up -d
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>Change the path to where your docker compose file is located&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Set the task as disabled, and run it manually from the context menu&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></content></item></channel></rss>